A Guide to the William H. Whyte papers FA272
Rockefeller Archive Center
- Personal, 2
  - Speeches, 1966-1990
    - Easements: Speech and Outline, 1974 March 9 (Box 28, Folder 492)
      Talk on "The Potentials of the Easement Approach," presented at French and Pickering Creeks Conservation Trust conference, and outline.
    - IDEA Conference,Syracuse, NY, 1973 September 24 (Box 28, Folder 493)
    - Marine Corps School: The Guadalcanal Campaign: The Japanese Viewpoint, 1945-1946 (Box 28, Folder 494)
      Lecture by Whyte, March 5. 1945.
    - New York and Tokyo: Colloquia on the City, Japan Society, 1975-1977 (Box 28, Folder 495)
      Whyte spoke on Planning and the People at the Fifth Session, held at the International House of Japan, on April 5-7, 1976. The talk is not found in the file.
    - Notes: Talks and Reports, 1982-1983 (Box 28, Folder 496)
    - Open Space and Retroactive Planning, 1958 May 20 (Box 28, Folder 497)
      Talk to the American Society of Planning Officials.
    - Partners, Livable Spaces, Undated (Box 28, Folder 498)
      Whyte's comments on "Aging Cities: Damn the Demographics, Full Speed Ahead," reproduced in unidentified publication.
    - Planning and the Study Group Industry, 1964-1967 (Box 28, Folder 499)
      Includes clippings as well as speech.
    - The Psychology of the Pedestrian, 1982 October 8 (Box 28, Folder 500)
      Section also entitled "The Gifted Pedestrian." Prepared for the Pedestrian Conference, Boulder, CO.
    - Rouse, Jim, 1978 (Box 28, Folder 501)
      Whyte's commentary on "The City of the Future," in response to Jim Rouse. Presented at the Conservation Foundation's thirtieth anniversary symposium, December 1, 1978.
    - St. Andrew's Anniversary, Cameron, Bill, 1980 (Box 28, Folder 502)
      Fiftieth anniversary of St. Andrew's School, Middletown, DE, luncheon address, October 4, 1980; Whyte's recollections of "Bill Cameron, Editor," january 4, 1982.
    - The Social Life of Small Urban Spaces and Lessons for Design, 1977 May 16 (Box 28, Folder 503)
    - Sustainable Cities Symposium, 1989-1990 (Box 28, Folder 504)
    - Walls: Text and Lecture Slides, c. 1987 (Box 28, Folder 505)
      File contains a Master List of Slides; a study of the movement of people at the Walls exhibition, March 5, 1987; and photographs of the Walls exhibit boards. There is no information on a lecture.
    - The Woodlands Conference, 1990 October 26 (Box 28, Folder 506)
      Talk entitled "Face to Face in the Center."
  - Whyte, Jenny Bell, 1990 (Box 28, Folder 507)
    Restricted - Confidential material.
  - Writings About Whyte, 1953-1993
    - General, 1976-1992 (Box 28, Folder 508)
    - Biography: Design and Environment, 1974 (Box 29, Folder 509)
      "Watching a People Watcher," by Susan Braybrooke.
    - Clippings, 1975-1983 (Box 29, Folder 510)
    - Clippings: Dallas, Charlotte, 1982-1985 (Box 29, Folder 511)
    - Clippings, Articles, Posters, 1976-1987 (Box 29, Folder 512)
    - Clippings, Press Releases, Reviews, Exhibits, 1985-1993 (Box 29, Folder 513)
    - Interview: Citicorp Critique, Undated (Box 29, Folder 514)
    - Linday, Nancy, Article, 1978 (Box 29, Folder 515)
    - Magazine Articles, 1981-1990 (Box 29, Folder 516)
    - Organization Man: Recent Clippings, 1979-1989 (Box 29, Folder 517)
    - Street Life Project, 1976-1988 (Box 29, Folder 518)
  - Writings By Whyte, 1944-1989
    - Aldrich Family Script Attempt, Undated (Box 29, Folder 519)
    - Articles, 1953, 1960s (Box 29, Folder 520)
      File contains "The Transients," Fortune, 1953; and manuscript and draft of "The Study Apparatus."
    - Articles, 1970-1979 (Box 29, Folder 521)
    - Articles, 1980-1989 (Box 29, Folder 522)
    - Casual Writers, 1953 (Box 29, Folder 523)
      Includes draft of Whyte's "The Casual Writers: A Layman's Guide to Sophisticated English."
    - Confluence Forum, 1954 (Box 30, Folder 524)
      Individualism in Suburbia, July 1, 1954.
    - Connecticut's Future, 1978 (Box 30, Folder 525)
    - Downtown Demographics, 1989 (Box 30, Folder 526)
    - Fiction Attempts: "The Party" et al., Undated (Box 30, Folder 527)
    - Generosity of Spirit, Undated (Box 30, Folder 528)
    - How to Do a Fortune Story, 1953-1979 (Box 30, Folder 529)
      File contains Whyte's Fortune articles on The Future: Park Forest and The Outgoing Life (both 1953), a report by the Task Force on the Preservation of Natural Beauty, and a draft of How to Back into a Fortune Story (1979)
    - Is Anybody Listening?: Advertising, 1952 (Box 30, Folder 530)
    - Is Anybody Listening?: Article, Undated (Box 30, Folder 531)
    - Is Anybody Listening?: Publication, Royalties, 1952 (Box 30, Folder 532)
    - Is Anybody Listening?: Reviews, 1952 (Box 30, Folder 533)
    - Last Landscape, 1968-1977 (Box 30, Folder 534)
    - Marine Corps School: "Battle Circuit": Radio Script, 1944 (Box 30, Folder 535)
    - Marine Corps School: Chapter One, 1946 (Box 30, Folder 536)
    - Marine Corps School: Chapter Two, 1946 (Box 30, Folder 537)
    - Marine Corps School: "The Colonel" - Incidents, 1946 (Box 30, Folder 538)
    - Marine Corps School: Guadalcanal, Undated (Box 30, Folder 539)
    - New York and Tokyo: A Study in Crowding, 1978-1984 (Box 30, Folder 540)
    - Nighttime Stories, Undated (Box 30, Folder 541)
    - Notes, General, Undated (Box 30, Folder 542)
      One page outline of good omens concerning center city parks.
    - Outline: Rediscovery of the Street, Undated (Box 30, Folder 543)
    - Philadelphia Story, 1948 (Box 30, Folder 544)
    - Play: "The Silver Box", Undated (Box 30, Folder 545)
    - Poem: Toffenetti Spaghetti, Undated (Box 30, Folder 546)
    - Writing for Fortune, 1952-1979 (Box 30, Folder 547)
      File contains copy of "How to Back into a Fortune Story" and a 1952 memo on writing for Fortune and the magazine's future direction.
    - Fortune Articles, 1949-1958 (Box 30, Folder 548)
- Audiovisual Materials, 3
  Series 3: Audiovisual Materials consists primarily of slides, and also includes films documenting Whyte's research as well as photographs and slides Whyte used for research, presentations, and projects. This series also contains one file of personal slides, which provide a glimpse of Whyte's life outside of his work, and one file of photographs of Whyte.
  - W.H.Whyte Series of Observational Films, 1
    As the mentor for initiatives such as the Project for Public Spaces and the Street Life Project in the 1960's and 1970's, William H. Whyte based his theories about urban planning and social movement on hours of footage and time-lapse photographs.
    The collection of edited films held at the RAC come from Whyte's work with the American Conservation Association and his role as an advisor to Laurance Rockefeller. A majority of the Whyte films are unedited trims and original clips, compiled into final films at a later date.
    Alphabetical.
    All inquires to view films require advanced notice of at least 24 hours, and may necessitate notice of up to one week. Individual items, including those not available in modern formats, may be restricted from scholarly access at the discretion of RAC.
    When requesting to view films -- please refer to the Title and the AV Number (example: AV 1902).
    If the item does not have a designated AV number, please refer to the Title and the Film Number (which consists of a combination of Roman numerals and alphanumerics - example: III 14.1-6).
    - Assembly for Japan Society: Tokyo/New York Pedestrians, 1987 May; Silent, Color, 29 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1127)
      Conditions Governing Access note
      Access copy currently unavailable. Please contact a RAC archivist for further instruction.
      Scope and Contents note
      Unedited footage of various public areas in New York City and Tokyo, shot in regular speed and time lapse.
    - Pilot A Outtakes (100% Conversation), Silent, Color, 7 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1132)
      Unedited footage from various public parks throughout New York City; some duplicate footage as seen in AV 1125.
    - Plaza, Part 1, Silent, Color, 10 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1129)
      Access copy currently unavailable.
      Unedited footage from various public parks throughout New York City; some duplicate footage as seen in AV #1125
    - Plaza, Part 3, Silent, Color, 9 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1130)
    - The Social Life of Small Urban Spaces, 1979; Sound, Color, 55 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1125)
      A finished film written and narrated by Whyte, examining trends in social movement based on footage shot throughout New York City and other locations. Supported by the Municipal Art Society of New York.
    - Sunken Plazas, Other Places, Silent, Color, 6 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1128)
    - Triangulation, Silent, Color, 3 minutes; 16mm film (Reel AV 1131)
  - Projects and Research: General, 1974-1990 (Box 31, Folder 549)
    95 slides
  - Projects and Research: Awnings and Arbors, 1983-1988 (Box 31, Folder 550)
    23 slides
  - Projects and Research: Blank Walls, 1980-1987 (Box 31, Folder 551)
    98 slides
  - Projects and Research: Blank Walls, 1980-1987 (Box 31, Folder 552)
    96 slides
  - Projects and Research: Blank Walls, 1980-1987 (Box 31, Folder 553)
    56 slides
  - Projects and Research: Business Improvement Districts, 1983-1992 (Box 31, Folder 554)
    97 slides
  - Projects and Research: Business Improvement Districts, 1983-1992 (Box 31, Folder 555)
    40 slides
  - Projects and Research: Campuses, 1977-1989 (Box 31, Folder 556)
    93 slides
  - Projects and Research: Charts, undated (Box 31, Folder 557)
    70 slides
  - Projects and Research: Concourses and Skyways, 1982-1987 (Box 31, Folder 558)
    80 slides
  - Projects and Research: Doorways, 1981-1985 (Box 31, Folder 559)
    9 slides
  - Projects and Research: Dusk Light, 1983-1987 (Box 31, Folder 560)
    8 slides
  - Projects and Research: Easements, 1983-1990 (Box 31, Folder 561)
    33 slides
  - Projects and Research: Food, 1982-1987 (Box 31, Folder 562)
  - Projects and Research: Food, 1982-1987 (Box 31, Folder 563)
    35 slides
  - Projects and Research: Good Spaces, 1980-1986 (Box 31, Folder 564)
    32 slides
  - Projects and Research: Interior Spaces, 1981-1990 (Box 32, Folder 565)
    99 slides
  - Projects and Research: Interior Spaces, 1981-1990 (Box 32, Folder 566)
  - Projects and Research: Parks and Gardens, 1982-1987 (Box 32, Folder 567)
    92 slides
  - Projects and Research: Parks and Gardens, 1982-1987 (Box 32, Folder 568)
    2 slides
  - Projects and Research: Places and Spaces, 1982-1990 (Box 32, Folder 569)
  - Projects and Research: Places and Spaces, 1982-1990 (Box 32, Folder 570)
    26 slides
  - Projects and Research: Plazas, undated (Box 32, Folder 571)
    100 slides
  - Projects and Research: Plazas, 1973-1986 (Box 32, Folder 572)
    81 slides
  - Projects and Research: Primes, 1987-1989 (Box 32, Folder 573)
    4 slides
  - Projects and Research: Scenic Roads, 1957-1988 (Box 32, Folder 574)
    91 slides
  - Projects and Research: Sitting and Spacing, 1973-1987 (Box 32, Folder 575)
  - Projects and Research: Sitting and Spacing, 1973-1987 (Box 32, Folder 576)
  - Projects and Research: Sitting and Spacing, 1973-1987 (Box 32, Folder 577)
  - Projects and Research: Sitting and Spacing, 1973-1987 (Box 33, Folder 578)
    94 slides
  - Projects and Research: Steps and Entrances, 1973-1990 (Box 33, Folder 579)
  - Projects and Research: Steps and Entrances, 1973-1990 (Box 33, Folder 580)
    71 slides
  - Projects and Research: Street Life: Al Fresco, 1986-1987 (Box 33, Folder 581)
    17 slides
  - Projects and Research: Streetscapes, 1982-1986 (Box 33, Folder 582)
    78 slides
  - Projects and Research: Streetscapes, 1982-1986 (Box 33, Folder 583)
    13 slides
  - Projects and Research: Sun, 1980-1990 (Box 33, Folder 584)
  - Projects and Research: Sun, 1980-1990 (Box 33, Folder 585)
  - Projects and Research: Sun, 1980-1990 (Box 33, Folder 586)
  - Projects and Research: Sun, 1980-1990 (Box 33, Folder 587)
    49 slides
  - Projects and Research: "The War Against the Street", undated (Box 33, Folder 588)
    74 slides
  - Projects and Research: Water and Trees, 1973-1987 (Box 33, Folder 589)
  - Projects and Research: Water and Trees, 1973-1987 (Box 33, Folder 590)
    12 slides
  - International: Canada, 1985-1989 (Box 33, Folder 591)
  - International: Canada, 1985-1989 (Box 33, Folder 592)
    55 slides
  - International: Jerusalem, 1986 (Box 34, Folder 593)
  - International: Jerusalem, 1986 (Box 34, Folder 594)
    54 slides
  - International: London, 1983-1986 (Box 34, Folder 595)
  - International: London, 1983-1986 (Box 34, Folder 596)
  - International: London, 1983-1986 (Box 34, Folder 597)
    11 slides
  - International: Tokyo, 1977-1981 (Box 34, Folder 598)
  - Midwest: United States: General, 1976-1989 (Box 34, Folder 599)
  - Midwest: United States: General, 1976-1989 (Box 34f, Folder 600)
  - Midwest: United States: General, 1976-1989 (Box 34, Folder 601)
  - Midwest: United States: General, 1976-1989 (Box 34, Folder 602)
    59 slides
  - Midwest: United States: Ohio, 1980-1990 (Box 34, Folder 603)
  - Midwest: United States: Ohio, 1980-1990 (Box 34, Folder 604)
  - Northeast: United States: General, 1976-1987 (Box 35, Folder 605)
  - Northeast: United States: General, 1976-1987 (Box 35, Folder 606)
    87 slides
  - Northeast: United States: Massachusetts: Boston, 1980-1990 (Box 35, Folder 607)
  - Northeast: United States: Massachusetts: Boston, 1980-1990 (Box 35, Folder 608)
  - Northeast: United States: Massachusetts: Boston, 1980-1990 (Box 35, Folder 609)
  - Northeast: United States: Massachusetts: Boston, 1980-1990 (Box 35, Folder 610)
  - Northeast: United States: Massachusetts: Boston, 1980-1990 (Box 35, Folder 611)
  - Northeast: United States: New York City Places, 1980-1990 (Box 35, Folder 612)
  - Northeast: United States: New York City Places, 1980-1990 (Box 35, Folder 613)
    29 slides
  - Northeast: United States: New York: Grand Central Area, 1977-1987 (Box 35, Folder 614)
    83 slides
  - Northeast: United States: New York: Greenacre Park, Paley Park, Washington Market Park, 1980-1986 (Box 35, Folder 615)
    47 slides
  - Northeast: United States: New York: Lincoln Center, 1980-1982 (Box 35, Folder 616)
  - Northeast: United States: New York: Lincoln Center, 1980-1982 (Box 35, Folder 617)
  - Northeast: United States: Pennsylvania: Penn's Landing, 1989 (Box 35, Folder 618)
  - Northeast: United States: Pennsylvania: Penn's Landing, 1989 (Box 35, Folder 619)
  - Northeast: United States: Pennyslvania: Philadelphia, 1982-1988 (Box 36, Folder 620)
  - Northeast: United States: Pennsylvania: Philadelphia, 1982-1988 (Box 36, Folder 621)
  - Northeast: United States: Pennsylvania: Pittsburgh, 1980-1989 (Box 36, Folder 622)
  - Northeast: United States: Pennsylvania: Pittsburgh, 1980-1989 (Box 36, Folder 623)
    10 slides
  - Northeast: United States: Pennyslvania: West Chester, 1982-1984 (Box 36, Folder 624)
    65 slides
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: South: General, 1980-1990 (Box 36, Folder 625)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: South: General, 1980-1990 (Box 36, Folder 626)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: South: General, 1980-1990 (Box 36, Folder 627)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: South: General, 1980-1990 (Box 36, Folder 628)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: South: General, 1980-1990 (Box 36, Folder 629)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: South: General, 1980-1990 (Box 36, Folder 630)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: South: General, 1980-1990 (Box 36, Folder 631)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: Southwest: General, 1976-1989 (Box 36, Folder 632)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: Southwest: General, 1976-1989 (Box 36, Folder 633)
    18 slides
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: Texas, 1980-1989 (Box 37, Folder 634)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: Texas, 1980-1989 (Box 37, Folder 635)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: Texas, 1980-1989 (Box 37, Folder 636)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: Texas, 1980-1989 (Box 37, Folder 637)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: West Coast: General, 1975-1990 (Box 37, Folder 638)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: West Coast: General, 1975-1990 (Box 37, Folder 639)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: West Coast: General, 1975-1990 (Box 37, Folder 640)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: West Coast: General, 1975-1990 (Box 37, Folder 641)
  - South, Southwest, and West: United States: West Coast: General, 1975-1990 (Box 37, Folder 642)
  - Personal: General, 1973-1990 (Box 37, Folder 643)
  - Personal: General, 1973-1990 (Box 37, Folder 644)
    66 slides
  - Photos: Photos of William H. Whyte, undated (Box 37, Folder 645)
    26 black and white photos
  - Slides: Notes on Slides, undated (Box 37, Folder 646)
  - Digital Media, 1985-1991 (Box 37, Folder 647)
    Contains separation sheets for 8 digital items
    - City Spaces - Human Places. Film by William H. Whyte. NOVA Series: Station WGBH; PBS Network., undated; 2014:FA272:051
      RAC is unable to provide access to obsolete media and original digital media. In addition separated media may not yet have undergone stabilization procedures. When feasible, a digital surrogate may be created via special order. All applicable charges will apply. See RAC Head of Archival Services or RAC Head of Digital Programs for details.
    - World Wildlife Fund Portrait, 1990; 2014:FA272:052
    - Preserving Family Lands. An address by Steve Small to the Red Hills Conservation Association, Tallahassee, Florida, 1991 March 28, 2014:FA272:053
    - The Landscape Architecture of Roberto Burle Marx, 1989; 2014:FA272:054
    - ON VIEW Symposium on Public Art, Harvard University, 1989 May 6, 2014:FA272:055
    - St. Andrew's School, Middletown, Delaware 19709, undated; 2014:FA272:056
    - William Whyte, Nightwatch; Today Show, 1989 April 5, 2014:FA272:057
    - Environnement, William Whyte, 1985; 2014:FA272:058